Welcome back, In this video we're going to
look at another example of cool
programing. This time let's move beyond
the simple hello world kind of examples
and on to something more exciting, say,
the ever popular factorial function. So,
in order to write factorial, we'll need to
open a file, which we can write some code.
Let me start that. And recall from last
time that every cool program has to have a
main class and the main class is required
to have a main method. And we don't care
what the main method return, so we'll just
have it return something a type object,
and then we'll just fill in a skeleton
here on the file. And, so now we're ready
to write some codes. So what are we going
to have the main method do? Well, before
we can actually write factorially, before
we can get to the guts of this program,
which is actually not very difficult. We
need to talk about IO some more. Because
we're going to need to be able to, read
and write, numbers. We need to be able to
read numbers from, the, the user who's
running the program, and print them back
out. So let's just review little bit about
IO, also. In order to invoke the IO
functions, we need an IO object. And one
of the IO functions is something that
prints out a string. So let's just, write
a program that we already know how to do,
just to confirm that we remember that.
And, we can compile this program. And it
should just print one. And, let's see.
Indeed it does. Okay? So it prints out the
number one. And so now, let's come back
here and let's talk about how to do input.
So, instead of just printing out the
number one, let's print out a strain that
the user types in. So, ins-, in here,
we're going to read a strain. And in order
to do that, we need an IO object because
there is another function, another method,
called in-strain. Okay. And so this will
renew this string. And return to string.
And to make sure that we get the nice
output let's concatenate on to that string
a new line. So, this is just to. When it
prints this string back out it will be
printed on i ts own line. So, let's try
compiling this, And steak. It compiles,
And now we can run spin. Remember the bang
command in UNIX runs the previous command
that began with the same letters. And now
the program runs and it waits. Cause it's
waiting for me to type something. And if I
type it type in one it prints back one and
if I type in 42 it gives me back 42. And
so now The next thing we need to talk
about is how to convert strings into
integers, because if we're going to do a
factorial, we want to work on integers and
not strings. And at the moment we're just
reading and writing strings. So, there is
a library written in cool that does
conversion between integers and strings.
And we're going to give the main class
here the functionality of that class.
Which is called A2I for ASCII to integer.
And that defines a bunch of methods, that
can convert between strings and integers.
So let's add those, commands in here. So
here, here's our string. That we've read
in. And what we want to do now is to,
convert this into an integer. So let me
just add a couple of parens here. So
there's our string, okay? And now we're
going to invoke. On that the method I'm
sorry we're going to call on that the
function the method, A to I. Okay? And
let's just double check here that we've
got friends in the right place. So that's
the argument to A2I. Now, we recall that
when we have a dispatch to a method and
it's just sitting by itself with not
object, it's dispatched to the self
object. And the self object is the object
of the current class that we're in. In
this case the main object, which has
inherited the A2I methods, And so the A2I
functions should be defined in there. Now
we have an integer. And we can do
something with that integer if we like.
So, let's add some more [inaudible] here
and let's just say we add just one to the
integer. Okay. And then once we're done
with our integer. Whatever operation it is
that we want to do with the integer we
need to convert it back to a string so
that we can print it out. An there's an
inverse fun ction IUA that will do. So, I
don't know if we have all the [inaudible]
in the right places at this point. So,
let's just check. Yes. That looks like
that should work. So this will, re-in a
string, convert, convert it to an integer,
add one to it convert it back to a string,
concatenate on a new line, and print it
out. Now let's see if all that actually
works, so let's run the compiler and we
have a problem here. It says that we have
an undefined class A to I. And the reason
is, we didn't supply the code for A2I. So
if we look in our directory here, we'll
see I've already copies in the class file
for A2I. And I encourage you to go and
look at that code. It's actually
interesting code to see how the
[inaudible] are written in [inaudible].
But now [inaudible] talk about how to
compile a program that uses a library, And
the way you do it is very simple. You just
list all the class files on the command
line when you call up the compiler. And it
will read them all in and treat them as a
single program. So in this case we
compile, compile fact together with A2I.
And that complies. And then we can run it.
[sound]. And now, if I type in three, it
prints four. And if I type in one, it
prints two. And so the program seems to be
working. And now we're almost ready to
write our factorial function. So what do
we want to do in factorial? Well, we want
to do something other than just adding
one. Instead, we want to call, our special
function factorial. So let's insert a call
to factorial in here. Okay, and let's get
rid of the plus one. And then let's check
that we have all the parens that we need.
So we need to close off the, the A2I call,
the factorial call, The I2A call. And then
that last one should be the out string
call, And it is, Okay. So now we can add a
method fact to this class, And fact is
gonna take an integer argument. So we need
a parameter here, And it's type is in
force. And the whole thing is gonna return
an integer. And then we have body of our
function, And probably a good idea here,
just to make sure that we got this much
right, to do something simple. So let's
just try to make a function that returns
one more than it's argument. So this will
do exactly the same thing that we had
before and let's just confirm that, that
is working. So EW compile with the A2I
library and now we have a syntax error.
And we see that I forgot the closing
semicolon here for the method. Remember
the, the, class body is a list of methods,
and each method is terminated by a
semicolon, Must try compiling that again.
Now it compiles. Let's run it. We type in
four gives a spec five. Alright, So looks
right we're ready now to actually right
the code for factorial. And this is gonna
be anti climactic because it's actually a
very simple code if we write it
recursively. So let's do that. So how's
that going to work? Well, everybody knows
the definition by Hardy Hope. If I is
equal to zero then the factorial of zero
is one. And we have a keyword there then
one, otherwise the factorial is going to
be I times, the factorial of I minus one.
Right, and then if statements in
[inaudible] always end in the keyword
[inaudible] so it's an if then else
[inaudible] construct. And that is
actually the entire definition. So now we
should have a program that actually
computes factorial, it compiles, so now
let's run it. So factorial of three is
six. And factorial of six, is 720 and that
looks right. And if we try it one more
time with a bigger number, we get a, we
get a large number, we think that's
probably correct. And so, anyway our
factorial function, is working. So, now
let's come back here, and just as an
exercise, let's rewrite this code
iteratively. So instead of using a
recursive function, let's write it using a
loop. And in order to that [inaudible]
gonna get rid of that code. What are we
going to need? Well, we're going to need
an accumulator here. We're going to need
a, a local variable that we can use to
accumulate the results of the factorial
computation. And the way you declare local
variables in [inaudible] is with
[inaudible] Statements, or naudibl
expressions. So we're gonna have, let's
call this, variable fact, for the, result
of factorial. And notice here that I can
have a variable that has the same name as
the function. And the programming
language, [inaudible] will not get
confused about that, Because variables and
functions, play different roles. So we'll
have the factorial fact, excuse me, it's
of type Int, and we do initialize it to
one. Alright, so that multiplication will
work. I think that the default for
integers is to be initialized to zero and
that would not be good if we're going to
be multiplying up fact with other with
other numbers. Alright, so then the, a let
has two parts. It has the variable or
variables that you are declaring. This
could actually be a list of variables.
We'll only have one this time. And then it
has a body. The, the expression or the
computation in which the fact variable is
available. And what do we want to do? So,
I think we're gonna need to have this be a
statement block 'cause we're gonna need to
have more than one statement in the
sequence. And we'll see why in just a
minute. But then we wanna have a loop. And
so what is our loop going to do? Well,
we're gonna say while I is not equal to
zero. What do we, and what do we need to
do the opening for the loop body the
opening keyword is called loop. [sound].
And now, I think we're going to need
another statement block here. So let's
open up a block. We're gonna probably need
to do more than one thing. The first thing
we want to do is we want to have fact. Be
fact times I, so we know that I is not
zero so we need to multiply the current
value of I into fact to accumulate the
result and then we want to subtract one
from I and notice that the assignment
statement in cool is this backwards arrow.
That's how you do assignment. It's also
how you do initialization. So,
initialization and assignment look the
same. Then we can close off our statement
block. Okay, so the body of a while loop
is always a single expression. In this
case, that expression is a block that
consists of two statements. [sound] And
then we can close the loop. And the
closing for a loop is the pool key word.
And then now we're in a statement block,
so this has to end with a semicolon.
Notice the statement block up there from
the let, And now we want the result of the
let block, or the let expression, to be
factorial. So whatever the, whatever we
got out of the while loop, whatever we
computed in the while loop, we want that
to be the result of the entire let
expression. [sound] so that's the last
statement of our blog. Remember the last
statement of a statement blog, is the
value of the blog. The body of the led is
the, the result of the led, so fact will
also be result of the whole led
statements, it's just the result of the
statement blog. And since the body of the,
factorial method itself is just the led
expression, fact will be the result of the
whole thing. And so this, if we've
written, haven't made any mistakes, should
be an iterative version of factorial. So,
let's compile this. And amazingly it
complies on the first try. And now let's
run it. [sound] And whoa! It actually
works. So we got six. And let's just do
one more test, to see that, to convince
ourselves that, things are working
reasonably well, and they are. Now, let me
just point out, one, common, mistake, that
you can easily make, and, that I make when
I haven't written cool programs for a
little while. If you're a C or programmer
or a Java programmer, you might, think
about, writing assignments, like this. So
I just use the equal sign to write
assignment. That looks completely fine if
you're, if you're familiar with those
languages, or used to programming in those
languages. And now, let's see what happens
when we try to compile this. Oh, it
compiles just fine. And then what happens
when we try to run it. Well it runs
[inaudible] input so let's give it input
and. Then we see that we've run out of
heat. And that looks like an infinite
loop. So we're going around and around the
loop And consuming memory for some reason.
And we'll, we '[laugh] get to that much
later in the class. Why, why this loop
actually ends up consuming memory. But,
clearly, we don't have enough memory, in
the loop, and, and eventually we run out.
And so, so that's a sure sign Of an
infinite look. So what is going on here?
Well the thing is that equals. Equals
operator in cool is the comparison
operators. [inaudible] Well we compared I
with O and that returns a boullion. So
these are perfectly valid cool
expressions. They just happen to be
boullions. So, you don't ever actually I
or factorial in this program. Your just
comparing fact with factoid body and I
with I minus one and the program is
perfectly happy to do that. It just
doesn't compute the factorial function.
And it never terminates, because I never
reaches zero. So that concludes our
factorial example. And we'll do one more
example next time of a more complicated,
of a, of a cool program with some
non-trivial data structures.