Hello again. In this video we're gonna
wrap up our overview of cool with one more
example of writing a cool program. For our
final example, let's look at a program
that actually manipulates some interesting
data structure. So, we'll begin here by
opening up a file, and let's call our
program list.cl this time. And as usual,
I'll begin by writing our main routine,
and our main method. And once again let's,
let's make this inherent for my O so we
can make my I, O routines here, and let?s
just begin with something very simple As,
as always. Let's just have something that
prints out; Hello world, but in a little
bit of an unusual way. Let's we're gonna
end up writing a list, a list
abstractions. And, let's first build a
list by hand, or at least build the
elements of a list by hand and then we'll
actually build the list abstraction and
put them in a list. So, and lets have some
strings, The line of our string, hello.
And this will also illustrate how you do
multiple let bindings, simultaneously; I
should say simultaneously, how you do
multiple let bindings in one let
expression. So you do them by just listing
them and, notice that this uses commas as
a separator rather than semicolons as a
terminator. So, this lead binding is going
to define three names of hello, world, and
newline. All of which are strings, And
then, We're going to now print these out
on the screen. So we're going to want to
be able to do out string, and since main
inherits himself we can do that without a,
without an object there cause just again a
dispatches to the self object. And we want
to concatenate these strings together in
the right order. So I'll do hello, dot
this is, hello is the string it can be
concatenated to world, and world is a
string so it can be concatenated to new
line. And that should do the job. And I'm
just [inaudible] one more thing about this
left this, these left bindings here. This
notice that the comma's, the comma's a
separator here meaning it doesn't come
after the last one in the list. So it just
separates that into the list, it's not a
terminator. And, now we can close up our
main procedure. [sound] Close up our class
definition. Save it. And now let's see if
it compiles. Oh amazing first try. And we
run it and it prints hello world, as
expected. So now, let's instead of
introducing the three strings separately
and then concatenate it together, let's
write an abstraction where we can build a
list of strings, and then that abstraction
will have a function within it to do the,
to do the concatenation. Alright so, have
our class called list and, every list
needs, I think they have two components.
So first it's gonna have the item that's
in the list and that'll be a string. And
then when you have a pointer to the next,
to the tail of the list, to the rest of
the list, and so we'll have a next field
to points, is another list of strength.
And now we need a couple of methods, In
order to use this list we'll need to be
able to initialize a list in some way. So,
the initialization function will take an
item and the rest of the list, the next
part of the list. And, what is it going to
do? Well let's go A to D to set the fields
of the objects. So this will have to be
done as a series of assignment statements.
So we'll need a statement block. And we
will set the item to be the I argument.
We'll set the next, attribute to be the N
argument. And now, we actually want this
initialized object here, this, this method
here to return the object itself. So that
and that'll be convenient for chained
together calls to unit. So, I'll have it
return self. It'll return the self object.
And that's the end of our statement block.
And then that is the end of our method,
And made a mistake up here. We have
declared the return type of [inaudible]
and what it's going to return of course is
an object of type list. We need to put a
list deceleration there. Alright, so that
takes care of [inaudible]. And now we can
use this to build, build a list down here.
So what should we do? Let?s actually have
a new variable called list. That we'll
introduce here in this lead, this series
of lead bindings. And let's just build a
list out of these three objects. So we'll
say, we'll have a new list, and then we'll
initialize it to contain the string hello.
What should the, rest of the list be, well
that should be another list which is
initialized to have the string world. And
what should be inside of that list? Well,
they'll have to be another new list
object. Which we'll initialize to have new
line, And now what do we put here?
Actually there's a little bit of a problem
here, isn't there? We need to put a list
object here. But we don't want to allocate
a, a new list object. We want that to be
really the equivalent of a, of a null
pointer. And there's no name for that in
Cool, actually. You can't write down the
name of a null pointer, it's called void
in Cool. There's no, there's no, no
special symbol for that. So we'll have to
create a variable that is just not
initialized. And that will be, so an
uninitialized variable of type list will,
in fact, be void. It'll be a null pointer.
So let's call that nil. And it'll be
uptight list and no initializer and so nil
there will point to nothing or the
[inaudible] and then we can use nil to
terminate our list here and then we have
to close off all the parans for all
nesting here and I think that's it and so
that will be our list. Okay? So I have a
list of three strings, and now what we
want to do with that is to print it out.
And so what we would like to do is to have
a list, call it the list, and a function
that's going to flatten that list, and
we'll just print it. So, that is the, what
the, what the main program should do. And
now You have to write the flatten
function. So flatten takes no arguments
and it's going to return a string, it's
going to return a single string. And
flatten is pretty simple function. What we
have to do, well, There's really two
cases. One is if we're at the end of the
string and the other is if we're not yet
at the end of the string. So, let's test
for that. So, how do we know if we're at
the end of the s tring? Well, if the next
pointer is, is void then there's no,
nothing more in the string. There's
actually is a special test for that and
it's called the IS void function and it's
written like this. So, IS void of next.
Okay. So, the next field, so, the next
field is void. Then what are we going to
return? Oops. Well then the result here is
just the item, Whatever the item was in
this last element of the list, and
otherwise. What do we want to do? Well,
otherwise we want to take the item and we
want to [inaudible] onto it. The results
of flattening the rest of the list, And
that is our flatten method. So let's see
if that works. So let?s compile this. And
we got a couple of Syntax errors here so
let's go back and see what's going on. So
we have a syntax error here. At the end of
the, the flatten method. And we see that
we left out the [inaudible] to close a
conditional. So a conditional has to be
ended with, with [inaudible]. Alright.
[sound] And let?s see if that's working
now. [sound] And we slide this syntax
error, I at line 29, and the mistake here
is that we forgot to declare the type of
this variable which is a list. And then it
gets initialized to this, to this big
expression that, we wrote out. Let me just
do the indentation a little more nicely
here. And notice something actually is
worth mentioning here. That this
definition here, this definition of the
variable list. It depends on the
definition of the previous variables in
the left. So each of so when a let binding
is made the name the variable that's bound
is actually available in subsequent let
expressions. So in this case this variable
list makes use of all of hello world and
new life Which were defined earlier in the
same let construct. Alright let?s save
this. [sound] And come over here and
compile it. And we see if we got another
bug in the, in the code. So if we come up
here, we see that we've, [inaudible] made
a mistake here, I've used functional
notation here, calling flattened of next.
And what I actually wanted to do was to
dispatch to nex t on the method flatten,
so that should be written like that.
Alright, probably getting close now. Let's
see if it works yet. Well it compiles. And
now let's see if it runs. And indeed it
does. It prints out hello world, just as
we expected. Now let's go back to our
program and let's generalize this list
abstraction in one way. Let's say that we
can have an arbitrary list of objects, not
just strings and that will require us to
change a few things so it can be
initialized now with an object. And now
when it comes down to flatten this list we
want to produce a string, we want to
produce, produce a print representation.
But not everything in the, in the list, is
necessarily a string. And we need a way to
traverse the list and do different things
for different kinds of things that might
be in the list, for different types of
things that might be in the list. And so
there's a constructing [inaudible] for
recovering the type of an of an object, at
run time, and this is called the case
construct. So let me first introduce a
[inaudible] expression here. We'll let the
string that we're gonna construct. Which
is of type string. [sound] And, that's
going to be initialized to something and
now it?s going to be a case and what are
we going to case on? It's going to depend
on the kind of thing the item is. So the
items in the list could be different kinds
of types and we want to do different
operation depending on what item actually
is. So do case item and the keyword is of,
and now we have different branches of the
case expression for different kinds of
things that could be in the list, let?s
say if it is an int-. Okay, so what this
does, is this, this says that if the item
is an int, then we're gonna rename it to
I. We're gonna bind I to that integer and
then we could do something with I. And
what would we want to do with I. Well,
we'd probably want to convert it, to a, to
a string. So, I'll do I two A of I. And
what if in fact That item happened to be
of type string? The item in the list
happened to be of type string. Wel l, then
we can just use the item itself, as the
string representation. And we could do
this for other kinds of types. If we had
other kinds of types in our system, we
could continue to, to list out other,
cases here and how to convert them into a
string representation. But let's just have
a default case here. We'll say if it's any
other kind of type, which would, which we
covered by having, a branch saying that if
it's of a type object, we'll call it O,
then we should just abort. And so we
should just call the word function and
quit. And that's our case. It needs to be
terminated with, my closing keyword called
Esack, and the reverse of, of case. And
now we can use that string that we
constructed in our, little function here.
So if, if, the next field is void then
we're just going to return the string.
Otherwise, we're gonna return the string
concatenated, with the flattening out of
the rest of the list. Okay Now there's a
couple of things we have to fix up. We
used the I2A method here, which means that
list needs to inherit From the, conversion
class A2I. And there's another issue here,
I see. And that's right here. So, if you
notice The, the. The case statement needs
to produce a string. Okay. And it turns
out that abort does not return a string.
Abort actually terminates the program, but
its type is that it returns an object. And
so here we have to convince the type
checker to convince, to accept this, piece
of code. And we need to get this branch
here to type as a string. So what we can
do, and this is ugly, but it's the way to
do it, is we put it in a, in a block in a
statement block. We call Abort First, and
again that will just terminate the
program. And now we can put any string
expression we want after that, and that
will be the, that will give a type string
to the entire block. So we can just put
the empty string here for example, and
then as we terminate it with a semicolon
since this isn't a block. And we can close
that with a curly brace. Okay, so this is
just something we have to do to make the
typ e checker happy. And that may be
everything we needed to do. So let's try
compiling this. And we have to include
the, the Virgin library. And we have one
syntax error So far, And that's because we
forgot to put the, semicolon terminator
on, on each of our, each of the, each of
the, variables that we were introducing on
the left. Okay you've got to save that,
let's try this again. And oops, I didn't
actually managed to fix the syntax here
and that's because I put the semicolon in
the wrong place. Actually, if I forgot the
Variables that are bound in a let, or
separated by commas, But the branches of
the case have to be terminated by semi
colons. So what I said before was
incorrect about using semi colons to
terminate let bindings it just in case
branches where we need it, in this
example. Anyway, coming back to this let
see if it compiles, and it does. And now
let?s run it. And it works. Now we of
course we haven't actually exploited the
ability to have different types of objects
in the list. So let?s, let's do that.
Let's add an integer in here. Type INT and
let's give it, the number 42. And, we can
insert it in here. And now we can pass any
object to a nit in the first position. So
we'll just put in 42 right there. And when
we compile and run this it should print,
hello world 42. If we, if everything goes
as expected, And it does, And that
concludes our little tour of [inaudible].
There are a couple of features that we
haven't shown, in these examples; but, you
can look in the examples directory, for
lots more programs. Many more programs
that will show you all the different, ins
and outs and details of the other language
features, as well as the ones we've
covered here.