[inaudible] Welcome back. This is the
first video in our long series of the
implementation of compilers, The call from
last time that a compiler has five phases.
We're gonna begin by talking about lexical
analysis and this will probably take us
three to four videos to get through at
least and then we'll, we will be moving on
in order to the other phases. Let's start
by looking at a small code fragment. The
goal of lexical analysis is to divide this
piece of code up. Into lexical units so
things like the keyword if the variable
names i, n, j and the relational operator
double-equals and so on. Now as a human
being this is. As we discussed last time
this is a very easy thing to do because
there are all kinds of visual clues about
where the units lie Where the boundaries
between the different units lie but a
program like lexical analyzer. It doesn't
have that kind of luxury. In fact what
the, what the likes of analyzer will see
is something that looks more like this. So
here I overwritten, the code out just as a
string, with all the white space symbols
included and is from, from this
representation, this is a linear string,
you can think of this as bytes in the file
that the lexical analyzer has to work and
it's going to mark through, placing
dividers between the different units. So,
it will recognize that there's a division
there, between the white space and the
keyword. Then a division after the keyword
and there's more a wide space, the open
paren, the i, another wide space, double
equals and so on and it goes through
drawing these lines diving up. The, the
string into its lexical unit, So I won't
finish the whole thing but you should get
the idea. Now, it doesn't just place these
dividers in the string however. It doesn't
just recognize the substrings. It also
needs to classify the different elements
of the string according to their role. We
call these token classes. Or sometimes,
I'll just call it the class of the token.
And in English, these roles are things
like noun, verb, adjective. Okay and there
is, ther e are many more or at least or
some more. And in the programming
language, the classes, the token classes
would be things like identifiers,
Keywords. I, and then individual pieces of
syntax like an open paren or a close
paren, those are the classes by
themselves. A, numbers. And again, there
are more classes but there's a thick set
of classes and each one of these
corresponds to some set of strings that
could appear in a program. So token
classes correspond to sets of strings, And
[inaudible] strings can be described
relatively straightforwardly so for
example. The token class of identifiers in
most programming languages might be
something like strings of letters or
digits, starting with a letter. So for
example, a variable name or identifier
could be something like a1 or it could be
f00 or it could be, b17, all of those
would be, be valid identifiers and often,
often they'll be additional characters
that allowed identifiers but that's the
basic idea, Very, very often The main
restriction identifiers that they have to
start, with a letter, An integer and
typical definition of an integer is a
non-empty string of digits. So, something
like zero or twelve. Okay. One followed by
two I should say is actually a string of
number in this case. And, and yeah, it is
actually whether admit some numbers you
might not think of. Things like 001 would
be a valid representation of a number or
even 00 could be a valid integer according
to this definition. Keywords are typically
just a fix set of reserved words and so
here I've listed a few, else, if, begin,
and so on. And then white space as itself
a token class so we actually have to say
in that string which is the representation
of the program what every character in
that string, what token or what token
class it's a part of. What every substring
is a part of and that includes the white
space. So, for example if we have a series
of three blanks, if I say if and then an
open paren and I have three blanks in
here, these three blank s would be grouped
together as white space. So the goal of
lexical analysis is to classify substrings
of the program according to their role.
This is the, the token class, okay? Is it
a keyword, a variable identifier, And then
to communicate these tokens, to the
parser. So, drawing a picture here, let's
switch colors. The lexical analyzer
communicates with the parser. Okay and the
functionality here is that, the lexical
analyzer takes in a string. Typically
stored up, also just a sequence of bytes
and then when [inaudible] to the parser is
sequence or pairs which are the token
class. And substring which I would say
string here, that, that, of which is the
sets of string which is a part of the
input along with the class the role that
it plays in the in the language, and this
pair together is called a token. So for
example, if my string is that f00 = 42,
all right, then that will go to the
lexical analyzer and that will come, I'll
write down here, three tokens. And these
would be identifier. Who? Operator say
equals. And. Integer, excuse me 42. And
here I just left these things as strings
to, to emphasize that these are strings.
So this is not the number 42 at this point
in time, it's, it's the string 42 which is
a plays an integer role in the programming
language. And then these, and when the
price that takes this input is this
sequence of pairs. So the lexical analyzer
essentially runs over the input string and
chunks it up into the sequence of pairs
where each pair is a token class and a
substring of the original input. As we
turn to the example from the beginning of
the video, here it is written out as a
string. And our goal now is to lexically
analyze this fragment of code. We want to
go through and identify the substrings
that are tokens and also their token
classes. So, to do this, we're gonna need
some token classes. So let's give
ourselves some of those to work with.
We'll need white space. And, and so this
is sequences of blanks, new lines tab,
things like that with the keywords. And
we'll need variables which we'll call
identifiers. And we'll need integers and
now I'll call those numbers. Here and then
we're going to have some other operations
some other classes things like open paren
close paren, and semi colon and these are
interesting. These three ae interesting
because they're single character token
classes that is, is a set of strings but
is only, is only one string in the set so
the open paren corresponds to exact
[inaudible] strings that contain only open
paren. So often the punctuation marks of
the language are in token classes all by
themselves. Another piece of punctuation
that we'll add here is, is assignments.
That will be a token class by itself
because it's such an important operation.
But, the double equals will class as a
relational operator with this class as an
operator put it up here. Alright, So now
what we're going to do is we're gonna go
through and tokenized this string and I'm
going to write down for each substring.
What class it is. You know, I'm just gonna
use the first letter here of the class.
It's indicated just to save time so I
don't have to write everything up. Hence,
we change colors so we can do this in a
different color. So, the first token here
is white space token and then that
followed by the F keyword. So, okay, And
then we have a blank here which is another
white space and then the open paren which
is its own token class so I'll just leave
it to identify itself there and then we
have an identifier. Okay, White space and
then an operator, the double-equals.
Another blank so that's white space
followed by another identifier followed by
close parens, Again, a punctuation mark in
a token class by itself. And then we have
three white space characters so those are
group together as a white space token,
Followed by another identifier and more
white space and then another single
character token, the assignment operator,
white space and a number, And then sem i
colon again and punctuation mark and a
token class by itself. Two white space
characters can group together. What
follows in is a keyword, so it gets
classified as in the keyword token class.
Another run of white space characters and
then another identifier. There's actually
a blank there where we almost covered it
up without marks. The assignment operator
by itself in a token class, white space, a
number, and finally the semi colon by
itself. And there is our tokenization.
We've identified the substrings and we've
also labeled each one with its token
class. To summarize, lexical analysis
implementation has to do two things. The
first job is to recognize the substrings
in the input that correspond to tokens.
And here's a little bit of compiler lingo
these substrings are called the lexemes.
So the words of the program are called the
lexemes. And then the second job is at for
each lexeme we have to identify its token
class. And then the output of the lexical
analyzer is a series of pairs which are
the token class. And lexing, Okay, And
this whole thing, one of these pairsis
called A token.