Welcome back. In this video, we're going
to take a little digression and talk about
formal languages. A formal language has
played a big role in theoretical computer
science but they're also very important in
compilers because inside of the compiler,
we typically have several different formal
languages that we're manipulating. A
regular expressions are one example of a
formal language but it's actually helpful
I think in understanding regular languages
and all the formal languages we'll see
later on in later videos to talk about
what the formal languages in general, So,
let's begin with the definition. A formal
language has an alphabet, So, some set of
letter sigma. And then a language over
that alphabet is just a set of strings of
the characters drawn from the alphabet. So
in the case or regular languages, we had
certain ways of building up sets of
strings of characters but other kinds of
languages would have different sets of
strings. And in general, a formal language
is just any set of strings over some
alphabet. An example of a language that
you're familiar with is a form from the
alphabet of English characters and it is
just the set of English sentences. Now,
This is not quite a formal language and
that we might disagree in which string of
English characters are in fact valid
English sentences but one could imagine
that we could define some rules that we
would say the certain strings are English
sentences and others aren't. And if we
could come to this on agreement this would
be a fully formal language. Now a much
more rigorous formal language would be
something like the following; we could
pick our alphabet to be the asking
character set and the language to be the
set of all Valid C program. So this is
definitely a very well defined language.
This is exactly the set of inputs that C
compilers will accept. And the, the
important contrast I want to draw here is
that the alphabet is actually interesting.
So, different formal languages, you know?
Have a very, very different alphabets and
we can't really talk a bout what the
formal language is or what sort of strings
we're interested in unless to find that
alphabet. Another important concept for
many formal languages is a meaning
function. Typically we have one of the
strings in our language and let's call
that some expression e and the expression
e by itself is just a piece of syntax.
It's a program in some sense or it
represents something else that we're,
Which is the thing we're actually
interested in. And so we have a Function L
that maps the strings in the language to
their meanings. And so for example in the
case of the regular expressions, this
would be a regular expression. And that
would be map to a set of strings. The
regular language that, that regular
expression to notes and we saw an example
where we wrote out the meeting function
for regular expression last time so let's
use regular expressions as an example and
I'm gonna first write down the meaning of
the regular expressions. The way I wrote
it down in the last video so if you recall
we had a regular expression epsilon and
that denoted a set, Which contain just one
string, namely the empty string. And then
we had a regular expression C for every
character in the alphabet which also do
need a socketing just one string namely
the single character C. And then, we had a
bunch of compound expressions. So for
example, A + B. That was equal to the
union of the sets A and B and we had the
concatenation so I could, I could
[inaudible] A and B and that was equal to
a cross product where I selected a string
from each set in order and concatenated
them together. And finally there was
iteration so I could write a star and that
was the union over I. Greater than zero of
all the sets A to the I, I ends. An
interesting thing about this definition is
you can see that they were mapping, over
we have expressions and let me switch
colors here, over here we have expressions
and over here we have the sets. But
there's something kind of odd about the
way this is written and not quite right
cuz you can see here we clearly, we have
an expression. We have a piece of syntax A
+ B and then somehow on the other side
this, this A, this A and this B have
magically turned into sets that we're
taking the union of and similarly down
here we're choosing an element from this
set but this set is also an expression and
what does that mean? Somehow we're
conflating the sets in the expressions and
this is what. The meaning function is
intended to fix and this what they, or,
or, or intended to make clear. So we, what
we really wanted to say is that there's
some mapping, That the language L epsilon
is the set so the, so L maps from
expressions into sets of strings. Okay,
It's a function that maps one to the other
and it you haven't seen this notation
before, this is a standard notation for
describing functions. It does says that L
is a function from things in the domain,
in this domain to this range, okay. And
similarly the language of this expression
is the set and it becomes really useful
for the compound expressions cuz here we
say the language of this expression. Is
equal to the language of a union with the
language of B and now you can see the
recursion. First we interpret A and B
using L and we take the union of the
result. Okay, so now it's clear what's
asset and what's an expression and
similarly here the language of a
concatenated with B, we are going to
select elements from the language of these
two expressions and then we're going to
form another set from those two sets. And
finally for iteration, The language of a
star is equal to the union over the
meaning of a bunch of expressions, A to
the I is an expression. This is a, a piece
of syntax and we have to convert it to A
set N order to take the union. And so
about this, is. The proper definition of
the meaning of regular expressions where
we've made the meaning function L explicit
and we've shown exactly how recursively we
apply L to decompose the compound
expressions into several expressions that
we compute the meaning of and then
computed the sets from those from those
separate smaller s ets. So, there's other
reasons for using a meeting function. We
just saw one of them which is to make
clear. What is syntax and what is
semantics in our definitions. Some parts
of the definition are expression and some
parts are the, the meanings or the sets
and the using L makes it clear that the
arguments to L are the, the programs or
the expressions and the results Are the,
the sets. The outputs are the sets, But
there are a couple of other reasons for
separating syntax and semantics. One, is
that it allows us to consider notation as
a separate issue. That is if we have
syntax and semantics being different, then
we can vary the syntax while we keep the
semantics the same and we might discover.
That there, that some kinds of syntax are
better than others for the problems that
we're interested in, for the languages
that we're interested in. And another
reason for separating the two is because
of expressions and meanings because syntax
and semantics are not in one to one
correspondents. And I actually illustrated
this with regular expressions in the
previous video but I want to iterate here
that, that there are generally many more
expressions than there are meanings so
that means there maybe multiple way. To
write an expression that means the same
thing. I'd like to take a moment to
illustrate why separating syntax from
semantics is beneficial for a notation.
So, everybody's familiar with the, the r
number system so I can write numbers like
zero, one. 42 and 107 and there are very
nice algorithms for describing how you add
and subtract and multiply such numbers but
there are older systems of notation for
numbers. Things like the Roman numerals. I
could have the number one. I could have
the number four, the number ten and say
the number 40 I think is written like that
and. And an issue with this number system,
first of all, let me stress that these two
have the same meaning. So the, the
meanings of expressions in this language
are. Are the integers and it's exactly the
same in this language. So the idea, the
mean ing of these two systems are just the
numbers but the notation is extremely
different. The number written in Roman
numerals was completely different from a
number written in Arabic numerals. And the
fact is that the Roman numerals are really
painfully to do addition and subtraction
and multiplication and in fact. Back in
ancient times when this was a common
system was not very well known how to do
it and very few people were actually good
at doing arithmetic with, with the system
because of, because the algorithms were
kind of complicated. And, when we moved to
the, the Arabic system, later, That it was
a big improvement because people, it was
easier for people to learn how to do basic
arithmetic with these kinds of numbers.
And the only thing that changed between
one system and the other was the system of
notation. And so, notation is extremely
important because it governs how you think
and it governs the kinds of things you can
say and the sort of procedures that you
will use. So don't underestimate the
importance of notation and this is one
reason for separating syntax from
semantics because we can leave the idea of
what we're trying to do than numbers
alone. And play with, with different ways
of representing them and we might discover
that some ways are better than others. The
third reason I gave for separating syntax
and semantics is that in many interesting
languages, multiple expressions, multiple
pieces of syntax will have the same
semantics. Now going back again to regular
expressions, let's consider the regular
expression zero*. Now there are many ways
to write the same language which is the
language of all strings of zeroes so
string of zeroes of any length. So for
example I could also write that as zero +
zero*. Another way to write it is as
epsilon + zero, zero* and here you can see
that, that this expression is all the
strings of 0s of at least link one and
then we get the empty string for epsilon
so that is = zero* and then just, you
know? Any combination of these things
would also amount to an eq uivalent
language for example that one and so on.
So there's actually an unbounded,
unlimited number of way I could write this
language but all of these mean exactly the
same thing and if you think about it. What
this means is that in general, if I draw
the two domains differently, I think about
different expressions over here and
different distinct meanings over here and
the function L that maps between them. The
function L is many to one. So there are.
Yeah. There are points in the space that
where many different expressions or pieces
of syntax map to the same meaning. And
this is just a general characteristic of
Interesting formal languages and this is
actually extremely important in compilers
because this is the basis of optimization.
The fact that there are many different
programs that are actually functionally
equivalent, that's what allows us to
substitute one program that runs faster
than another, that's what allows us to
replace one program with another if it
runs faster and does exactly the same
thing. So we couldn't do optimization and,
you know the reason we can do optimization
as precisely because the meaning function
is many to one. So meaning is many to one
and keep in mind, important point here
it's never one to many. We don't want the
opposite situation. If we have the
opposite situation, Where L could map a
single point to two different meanings.
Well first of all, this would no longer be
a function but, but also it would mean
that the meaning of certain expressions
say in our programming language was not
well defined. That's that when you wrote a
program was actually ambiguous whether it
meant this or it meant that and that's a
situation we don't like. So, we expect
meaning functions to be many to one for
nontrivial languages and we don't want
them ever to be one too many. And that
concludes today's video. Next time, Going
to go back and continue with our
discussion of lexical analysis.