In this video we're going to talk about
ambiguous context free grammars in
programming languages and what to do about
them. We'll begin by looking at our
favorite grammar for expressions over +
and * and identifiers and we'll just look
at the string id * id + id. Now it turns
out that this particular string and let's
write it down one more time, id * id + id.
This string has two parse tree using this
grammar. Let's do the Parse tree on the
left first. We begin with the start symbol
e and the first production in this
derivation that gives us this Parse tree
must be that e goes to e + e. E + e And
then we replace the left most e by e * e.
We use the production e goes to e * e and
we still have the plus e left over and at
this point you can see that we're going to
get this parse tree. We've done with those
two productions. We have done this much.
The construction of the parse tree and the
rest of productions are just generating
these id's. So that's a three more
productions and we can see that, you know
if we do those we'll get id * id + id no
problem, alright. So now let's switch and
do the derivation on the right or excuse
me, the parse tree on the right so this
begins also with e. But this time we use
the production e goes to e * e first, all
right? And now we're gonna replace the
right most e. By e goes to e + e so we
have e * e + e and now we've, with those
two productions we've done this portion of
the parse tree and once again with three
more productions we can get to id * id +
id so there you can see we've got two
derivations. That produced two distinct
Parse trees. And just to be completely
clear about this, in this case we're
getting two different Parse trees. Each of
these derivation, each of these Parse
trees has many derivations. Each Parse
tree has a left most derivation, a right
most derivation and many other
derivations. This situation is something
different. Here we have two derivations
that yield completely different Parse
trees and that is the sign or the
definition of an ambiguous grammar. So a
grammar is ambiguous if it has more than
one Parse tree for some string. And
another way of saying the same thing is
that there is more than one right most or
left most derivation for some string. So
if some string has two right most
derivations or more or two left
derivations or more then the, that string
will have two distinct parse trees and
that grammar will be ambiguous. Ambiguity
is bad. If you have multiple parse trees
for some program then that essentially
means that you're leaving it up to the
compiler to pick which of those two
possible interpretations of the program
you want it to generate code for and
that's not a good idea. We don't like to
have ambiguity in our programming
languages and leave decisions about what
the program means up to the compiler. Now
there are several ways to eliminate
ambiguity from a grammar and the most
direct method which we'll talk about first
is just to rewrite the grammar so it's an
ambiguous. That is to write a new grammar
that generates the same language as the
old grammar but it only has a single Parse
tree for each string. So here's a, a
rewrite of the grammar we've been looking
at and let's write down our favorite input
string one more time, id * id + id. And
let's look at how that string will be
parsed according to this new grammar so it
begin with the start symbol e and now
notice that e can no longer generate a
plus or a times. In fact we separated the
grammar now into two sets of productions,
two nonterminals and e controls the
generation of plus and e prime controls
the generation of multiplications, okay.
And so in originally of + we have to use
the production e prime + e. There is no
other way to do it. And now if we look at
e prime, what can e prime do? Well, e
prime can generate an identifier times
something and if you look at the grammar
that is the only production that can
generate identifier times something else.
The only other possibility involving times
is to generate apprenticed expression
which clearly won't match the string that
we're trying to pars E. So we have to use
this production Id * e prime. Well now in
order to match the string, we can see that
this e prime, the second, the one
remaining e prime here has to go to id
because sandwiched in between the times
and the plus is a single id, there's only
one production that will do that so that's
completely unique and determined. And
finally, we have the last e over here
which we want to use to produce an id.
Well how can we do that? Well, the e can
go to e prime. In fact it has to and then
the e prime can go to id by itself, and
there. We've manage to parse the string.
So in general what does this grammar
doing, well we do say we stratify the
grammar. We've divided the productions
into two classes. One that handles times
and one that handles times and there's one
nonterminal for each, each operator so.
The e productions control the generation
of plus and let's just look at what
happens with that. So if I, e can go to e
prime + e and just sticking with the e
productions, what can happen to this e
here? Well, we could do it again, E prime
+ e prime + e. And if we do it one more
time, we'll have e prime + e prime + e
prime + e. And in general, I think you see
the pattern, we can generate any number of
e primes summed together. And finally,
that trailing e, there's always one e left
at the end. Eventually that e, when we
want to stop generating pluses, has to be
rewritten to e prime. So in the end, we'll
get a sequence of pluses of, of e primes
separated by pluses, okay? That's what e
prime can do. I'm sorry, that's what e can
do. Now let's look at what e prime can do.
So, e prime. And let's just focus on the
first two productions. As we can see at
the first two productions are handling
identifiers times something and then the
last two productions are handling
parenthesized expression but you know I
hope you the symmetry that it's, it's
really the same idea for identifiers and
parenthesized expressions. So we'll just
do identifiers just to keep the slide from
getting too crowded. So e prime can go to
id * e p rime. Well, we can repeat that,
we can go to id. * id * e prime and we can
repeat that again and I hope you're
beginning to see the same pattern. This is
the same idea as with plus. And when we
wind up with n is a bunch of identifiers
multiplied together, alright. Because that
trailing e prime in this case, in the end,
can be rewritten to id. Now, in the case
of e prime there are actually two
alternatives. We could either be
generating id's or we could be generating
parenthesized expression. So really, for
each of these id's it could have been a
parenthesized expression. So let me just
write some parenthesized e's down here
just to remind us that we have an
alternative and in the end, we wind up
with, you know? A string of identifiers or
parenthesized expressions separated by
times, Okay? Alright right, so I hope you
see how this works. There's the, the way
that the grammar set up because we have
these two separate groups of productions.
All the pluses must be generated Before
any of the times. The times are gonna be
nested more deeply inside the Parse tree
than the pluses. The pluses are generated
at the outer most level and then the e
primes will generate the times inside the
pluses. And so the grammar enforces that
times is gonna buy more tightly than plus.
The last detail that's worth pointing out
here is I've noticed inside of the
parenthesized expression, we have an e,
not an e prime. And why is that? Well once
we're inside of a parenthesized
expression, the whole purpose of
parentheses is to show the explicit
association and so that we can have pluses
inside of times by using parentheses. And
that's all that, that, that's the
significance of using e in this part of
the grammar rather than e prime. To
review, We started out with a grammar and
A string we wanted to parse, id * id + id,
but that grammar gave us two distinct
Parse trees for the string and here are
the two Parse trees again. And by
rewriting the grammar, we were able to
eliminate this Parse tree on the right.
So, this Parse tree is no longer p
ossible. The Parse tree on the left is
modified, there's more symbols in it now.
I mean for example, this became an e prime
and there was a chain here of
non-terminals, this e went to e prime and
went to id and there was some other minor
changes in here so the Parse tree is not
exactly the same as before but. We were
able to get a parse where the times binds
more tightly than the plus. So, now let's
consider another interesting example. If,
then, else expressions were the else is
optional and here's one way to write that
grammar. Here we have a if, then, else And
the usual way. But then we also have a
production where there is no else. So
that's the case where the else is optional
and then maybe there are some other kinds
of expressions that we don't need to
concern ourselves with those. We'll just
focus on the if and else piece. The
problem is, at this particular if, then,
else expression has two possible Parse
tree. On the one hand, the else might
belong to the outer if, That is, this
particular. Inner if might have no else
and. The else would be associated with the
outer if. The other possibility is that
the else belongs to the inner if that we
have this structure if then else is nested
inside of an if then that has no else
statement. And in, what we want in on the
programming language I know of is the
second form. We want else's to associate
to the closest matching if then and not
one that's further away. We can write a
grammar to express the desired
association. The property we want is that
every else should match the closest
unmatched then. So whenever we see an
else, we want it to be associated with the
closest then that doesn't already have a
closer matching else. So that means that
the if statements are going to be divided
into two categories. We'll have the
matched if's, those that have all of the
then statements nested within them matched
with an else. And the unmatched if's where
some then's then expression inside of the
unmatched if that has no matching else.
So, when matched ifs look like, well tha
t's pretty straight forward, I, and if,
then, else is a matched if most have, must
have both of them and an else and any
nested if statements on both branches
must, must also have matching else's. And,
if you have any other kind of a constructs
that's not an if and else, that's also
considered a matched if. What about the
unmatched if's? One possibility is that
they, it's simply an unmatched if, that
there is no else. So we have if and then
and no matching else out here. And now the
crucial case, what if we have an if and
else? So that the top level if then has a
matching else but then the unmatched if is
somewhere inside. Well, then we claim that
the unmatched if has to be in the else
branch, it cannot be in the then branch.
The then branch must be a matched if. And
why is that? Well, think about it. If this
was an unmatched if, if this was an
unmatched if, that means that there will
be some then in here. That had no matching
else. And then this else here would be
closer to that then, than it is to this
end then. And so, we would have to match
that one according to our definition.
Okay. So, that situation is not possible.
So, the only possibility for an unmatched
if is that, that it's itself and if and
else is that, that the any if, then,
else's under their branch have to be
matched and the unmatched if and else has
to be in the else branch. So reconsidering
the expression we had before, we can see
that this else is supposed to match this
then. And so the association should be
like this, and, and therefore, this Parse
tree on the right is not the one that we
want and the grammar we gave on the
previous slide will parse the expression
according to this Parse tree on the left.
Now you might think of the unambiguous if,
then, else grammar is complicated and hard
to understand and frankly I would have to
agree with you. Unfortunately, it's
impossible to automatically convert an
unambiguous grammar to an ambiguous one,
so we have to do these conversions by
hand. If we're going to have unambiguous
grammars, we have t o figure out how to
write them by hand and that does result
insignificantly more complex grammars and
grammars that are hard to read and
maintain than if we use the, well more
straightforward ambiguous grammars. A
possibility is to we'll try to somehow
live with ambiguity cuz that will allow us
more depth natural definitions. And, but
then we would need some disambiguation
mechanism. We need some way to tell which
Parse tree we want when more than one
Parse tree is possible. In fact, most
practical parsing tools adopt the second
approach. So, instead of rewriting the
grammar, we used the more natural
ambiguous grammar and the tool provide
some kind of disambiguating declarations.
The most popular form of disambiguating
declarations are precedence and
associativity declarations. So, here is a
natural grammar for plus over the integers
and this is ambiguous even just with a
single infix operation, we can get
ambiguity because this grammar doesn't
tell us whether plus is left associative
or right associative. And. So, simple
solution here is to have associativity
declarations. So here, we declare plus to
be left associative and this is the
notation used in Bison. So, Bison is a
particular tool and a present left plus
declares that plus is a left-associative
operation and so that would rule out this
particular Parse tree over here. Here
[inaudible] more complex grammar
essentially the grammar we began with the,
at the start of this video. Here we have
plus and times over the integers and again
this grammar is ambiguous because it
doesn't say what the precedence of times
is with respect to plus. And the solution
for this is to have multiple associativity
declarations. We declare plus to be left
associative and we declare times to be
left associative and then the precedence
between plus and times is given by the
order. So the fact here that times appears
after. Plus means that times has a higher
precedence than plus. Just one word of
caution, These declarations are called
associativity and precedence declarations
but that's not what's quite what's going
on inside the parser. The parser doesn't
really understand about associativity and
precedence. Instead, these declarations
tell it to make certain kinds of moves in
certain situations. We won't really be
able to explain this until we get much
further into parsing technology, but just
be aware that we have to be a little bit
cautious in using these declarations.
Usually they behave like associativity and
precedence in the way you expect but there
are some situations in which they will
cause Rising behavior And is important
that you check the behavior of your
grammar after you add these declarations.