In this video, we're gonna begin our
discussion of parsing technology with
context-free grammars. Now as we know, not
all strings of tokens are actually valid
programs and the parser has to tell the
difference. It has to know which strings
of tokens are valid and which ones are
invalid and give error messages for the
invalid ones. So, we need some way of
describing the valid strings of tokens and
then some kind of algorithm for
distinguishing the valid and invalid
strings of tokens from each other. Now
we've also discussed that programming
languages have a natural recursive
structure, So for example in Cool, an
expression That can be anyone of a very
large number of things. So two of the
things that can be are an if expression
and a while expression but these
expressions are themselves recursively
composed of other expressions. So for
example, the predicate of an if is a, a
[inaudible] expression as is the then
branch and the else branch and in a while
loop the termination test is an expression
and so is the loop body. And context-free
grammars are in natural notation for
describing such recursive structures. So
within a context-free grammar so formally
it consist a set of terminals t, a set of
nonterminals n, a start symbol s and s is
one of the nonterminals and a set of
productions and what's a production? A
production is a symbol followed by an
arrow followed by a list of symbols. And
these symbols, there are certain rules
about them so the x thing on the left hand
side of the arrow has to be a nonterminal.
That's what it means to be on the left
hand side so the set of things on the left
hand side of productions are exactly the
nonterminals. And then the right hand side
every yi on the right hand side can be
either a nonterminal or it can be a
terminal or it can be the special symbol
epsilon. So let's do a simple example of a
Context-free Grammar. Strings of balanced
parenthesis which we discussed in an
earlier video can be expressed as follows.
So, we have our start symbol and. One
possibility for a string o f balanced
parentheses is that it consists of an open
paren on another string of balanced
parentheses and a close paren. And, the
other possibility for a string of balanced
parentheses that is empty because the
empty string is also a string of balanced
parentheses. So, there are two productions
for this grammar and just to go over the
to, to relate this example to the formal
definition we gave on the previous slide,
what is our set of nine terminals, it's
just. The singles nonterminal s, what our
terminal symbols in this context-free
grammar is just open and close paren. No
other symbols. What's the start symbol?
Well, it's s. It's the only nonterminal so
it has to be the start symbol but
generally we will, when we give grammars
the first production will name a start
symbol so rather than name and explicitly
whichever production occurs first the
symbol on the left hand side will be the
nonterminal for that particular
context-free grammar. And then finally,
what are the productions with the, we said
there could be a set of productions and
here are the two productions for this
particular Context-Free Grammar. Now,
productions can be read as rules. So,
let's write down one of our productions
from the from the example grammar and what
does this mean? This means wherever we see
an s, we can replace it by the string of
symbols on the right hand side. So,
Wherever I see an s I can substitute and I
can take the s out. If that important, I
remove the s that appears on the left side
and I replace it by the string of symbols
on the right hand side so productions can
be read as replacement rule so right hand
side replaces the left hand side. So
here's a little more formal description of
that process. We begin with the string
that has only the start symbol s, so we
always start with just the start symbol.
And now, we look at our string initially
it's just a start symbol but it changes
overtime, and we can replace any
non-terminal in the string by the right
hand side, side of some production for
that non-terminal. So for exam ple, I can
replace a non-terminal x by the right hand
side of some production for x. X in this
case, x goes to y1 through yn. And then we
just repeat step two over and over again
until there are no non-terminals left
until the string consist of only
terminals. And at that point, we're done.
So, to write this out slightly more
formally, a single step here consist of a
state which is a, which is a string of
symbols, so this can be terminals and
non-terminals. And, somewhere in the
string is a non-terminal x and there is a
production for x, in our grammar. So this
is part of the grammar, okay? This is a
production And we can use now production
to take a step from, to a new state Where
we have replaced X by the right hand side
of the production, Okay? So this is one
step of a context-free derivation. So now
if you wanted to do multiple steps, we
could have a bunch of steps, alpha zero
goes to alpha one goes to alpha two and
these are strings now. Alpha i's are all
strings and as we go along we eventually
get to some strong alpha n, alright. And
then we say that alpha zero rewrites in
zero or more steps to alpha n so this
means n zero, greater than or equal to
zero steps. Okay. So this is just a short
hand for saying there is some sequence of
individual productions. Individual rules
being applied to a string that gets us
from the string alpha string zero to the
string alpha n and remember that in
general we start with just the start
symbol and so we have a whole bunch of
sequence of steps like this that get us
from start symbol to some other string. So
finally, we can define the language of a
Context-Free Grammar. So, [inaudible]
context-free grammar has a start symbol s,
so then the language of the context-free
grammar is gonna be the string of symbols
alpha one through alpha n such that for
all i. Alpha i is an element of the
terminals of g, okay. So t here is the set
of terminals of g and s goes, the start
symbol s goes in zero or more steps to
alpha one, I'm sorry a1 to an, okay. And
so we're just saying, this is just saying
that all the strings of terminals that I
can derive beginning with just the start
symbol, those are the strings in the
language. So the name terminal comes from
the fact that once terminals are included
in the string, there is no rule of
replacing them. That is once the terminal
is generated, it's a permanent feature of
the string and in applications to
programming languages and context-free
grammars, the terminals are to be the
tokens of the language that we are
modeling with our context-free grammar.
With that in mind, let's try the
context-free grammar for a fragment of
[inaudible]. So, [inaudible] expressions,
we talked about these earlier, but one
possibility for a [inaudible] expression
is that it's an if statement or an if
expression. And, we call that [inaudible]
if statements have three parts. And they
end with the keyword [inaudible] which is
a little bit unusual. And so looking at
this looking at this particular rule, we
can see some conventions that way, that
are pretty standard and that we'll use so
that non-terminals are in all caps. Okay,
so in this case was just [inaudible] we'll
try that in caps and then the terminal
symbols are in, in lower case, all right?
And another possibility Is that it could
be a while expression. And finally the
last possibility Is that it could be
identifier id and there actually many,
many more possibilities and lots of other
cases for expressions and let me just show
you one bit of notation to make things
look a little bit nicer. So we have many
we have many productions for the same
non-terminal. We usually group those
together in the grammar and we only write
a non-terminal on the right hand side once
and then we write explicit alternative. So
this is actually. Completely the same as
writing out expert arrow two more times
but we here we just is, this is just a way
of grouping these three productions
together and saying that expr- is the
non-terminal for all three right hand
sides. Let's take a look at some of the
strings on the language of this Context-
Free Grammar. So, a valid Kuhl expression
is just a single identifier and that's
easy to see because EXPR is our start
symbol, I'll call it EXPR. And, so the
production it does says it goes to id. So
I can take the start symbol directly to a
string of terminals, a single variable
name is a valid Kuhl expression. Another
example is an e-th expression where e-th
of the subexpressions is just a variable
name. So this is perfectly fine structure
for a Kuhl expression. Similarly I can do
the same thing with the while expression.
I can take the structure of a while and
then replace each of the subexpressions
just with a single variable name and that
would be a syntactically valid cool while
loop. There are more complicated
expressions so for example, here we have a
why loop as the predicate of an if
expression. That's something you might
normally think or writing but perfectly
well form and tactically. Similarly, I
could have an if statement or an if
expression as the predicate of and if it's
inside of an if expression. So, so nested
if expressions like this one are also
syntactically valid. Let's do another
grammar, this time for simple arithmetic
expressions. So, we'll have our start
symbol and only non-terminal for this
grammar be called e and one of the
possibilities while e could be the sum of
expressions. Or and remember this is an
alternative notation for e arrow. It's
just a way of saying I'm going to use the
nonterminal for another production. We can
have a sum of two expressions or we could
have the Multiplication of two
expressions. And then we could have
expressions that appear inside the
parentheses, so parenthesized expressions.
And just to keep things simple, we could
just have as our base, only base case
simple identifier so variable names. And
here's a small grammar over plus and times
to see and in parentheses and variable
names. [inaudible] a few elements of this
language. So for example, a single
variable name is a perfectly good element
of the language id + id is also in this
language. Which s is id + id * id and we
could also use parens to group things so
we could say id + id * id that's also
something you can generate using these
rules and so on and so forth. There are
many, many more strings in this language.
Context-free grammars are our big step
towards being able to say what we want in
a parser but, we still need some other
things. First of all, a context-free
grammar at least as we define it so far,
just gives us a yes or no answer. Yes
something, yes a string is in the language
of the Context-free grammar or no it is
not. We also need a method for building a
Parse Tree at the input. So in those cases
where it is on the language, we need to
know how it's in the language. We need the
actual Parse Tree not just yes or no. In
the cases where the string is not in the
language, we have to be able to handle
errors gracefully and give some kind of
feedback to the programmer so we need a
method for doing that. And finally if we
have these two things we need an actual
implementation of them in order to
actually implement context-free grammars.
One last comment before we wrap up this
video. The form of the context-free
grammar can be important. Tools are often
sensitive to the particular you write the
grammar and while there are many ways to
write a grammar for the same language,
only some of them may be accepted by the
tools. And as we'll see there are cases
where it's necessary to modify the grammar
in order to get the tools to accept it.
This happens actually sometimes as well
with regular expressions but it's much
less common. So normally for most regular
expressions you would want to write the
tools would be able to digest them. That's
fine. That's not also true. That's not
true of an arbitrary context-free grammar.