In this video, we're gonna continue our
discussion of parsing with the idea of a
derivation. So a derivation is a sequence
of productions so beginning with the start
symbol, we can apply productions one at a
time. In sequence and that produces a
derivation. And a derivation can be drawn
in a different way instead of as a linear
sequence of replacements, we can draw it
as a tree. So for example, if I have a
nonterminal x it appears in a derivation,
then when I replace x, I can represent
that by making the children Of x, the left
hand side of the rule that I used to
replace x. So I applied production x goes
to y1 to yn, I add the y1 to yn is
children of x in the tree that I'm
building up. Let's do an example. Here is
our simple grammar of arithmetic
expressions and let's consider this
particular string id * id + id. So what
we're going to do now is we're going to
parse this string and we're going to show
how to produce a derivation for the string
and also at the same time build the tree.
And here it is, Over here, there is
derivation beginning in e and ending in
the string that we're interested in with
one production applied each step along the
way and here is the corresponding tree and
this is called a parse tree. This is a
parse tree of this expression or this
input string. So let's walk through this
derivation in detail. The right side in
red, we're going to have the tree that
we're building up. And on the left side in
blue, we're going to have the steps in the
derivation that we've taken so far. So
initially, our derivation consists of just
the start symbol e and our tree consists
of just the root which is also the start
symbol. So the first step is that we have
a production e goes to e + e and what that
means is over on the tree, we take the
root of the tree and we make, we give it
three children e + ne. So now, we replace
the first t by e * z. We use the
production e goes to e * z and that means
we take the first e in the tree and we
give it to three children, e *
[inaudible]. Continuing along we take the
fi rst e here that remains in this
expression and we replace it by id which
means we make id a child of the left most
e in the tree that we're building. And
then we replace the second e by id using
the production e goes to id and finally,
we use the same thing with the third e and
now, we have completed our Parse Tree. So
here again, from the start symbol to the
string, we were interested in parsing and
in the process we built up this Parse Tree
of the expression. Now there are lots of
interesting things to say about parse
trees. So first of all, parse trees have
terminals at the leaves and nonterminals
at the interior nodes and furthermore,
in-order traversal of the leaves is the
original input. So let's back up and look
at our example and confirm all this. If we
look at the leaves, we can see that they
are all terminals, Okay? And the interior
nodes are all nonterminals. In this case,
it's only one nonterminal in our language,
all the interior nodes are e and the
leaves are the terminals of the string.
And then we can see if we do an inward
reversal of the leaves, we get exactly
this input string that we started with.
Furthermore, the Parse Tree shows the
association of the operations and the
input string does not. So you may notice
here that the way that this Parse Tree is
constructed, the times binds more tightly
than the plus because the times is a
sub-tree. Of the tree containing plus. And
so this means that we would do the e * e
first before we would add e and some, some
of you may have wondered well, how did I
know. To pick this Parse Tree because
actually if you think about it, there's
another derivation. Actually there are
several derivations that will give me a
different Parse Tree where the plus, where
the times is towards the root and the plus
is nested inside the times. So let's not
worry about that for right now, and let's
just say that somehow we knew that this
was the Parse Tree we wanted and I gave
you a derivation that produces that Parse
Tree. Continuing on, the previous
derivation I showed you is actually a very
special derivation. It's what's called a
leftmost derivation where each step will
replace the leftmost nonterminal in our
string of terminals and nonterminals. And
there's a natural and equivalent notion of
a rightmost derivation and here it is.
Here is a rightmost derivation for the
same string. Again, beginning with the
start symbol ending with a string we're
interested in. And notice that at each
step, we're replacing the rightmost
non-terminal. So here, we replace the only
non-terminal e and we get e + c. And then
in the second step, we replace the second
non-terminal e with id and so on for the
rest of the string. So let's just
illustrate this entirely with our little
picture here of the tree and the
derivation simultaneously so once again
over here is our tree and this is the
root, the start symbol e and, and in blue
is our derivation so we begin by replacing
e by e + e. That's the only nonterminal so
it's the rightmost one and then working
from the right side of the tree, we
replace the right e by id and then the
left id gets replaced by e * z. And now
the right most e that remains is replaced
by id and finally the only e that remains
is also replaced by id. Now I want to
point out that the rightmost and leftmost
derivations I showed you have exactly the
same Parse Tree. And, this was not an
accident. Every Parse Tree has a rightmost
and a leftmost derivation. It's just about
the order in which the branches are added.
So for example, if I have the first
production e goes to e + e, now I have a
choice on how to build my tree. I can
either work on. This sub-tree or I can
work on that sub-tree. And if I build this
one first, that will be a rightmost
derivation. If I continue to always work
on the rightmost non-terminal of course,
And if I work on this one first, I can use
that to do a leftmost derivation. Now it's
important also to realize that there are
many derivations besides rightmost and
leftmost. I could, I could choose
non-terminals in some random order to do
my replacements. But th e rightmost and
leftmost ones are the ones that we're most
concerned with. So to summarize, we're not
just interested in whether a string is in
the language of a particular context-free
grammar, we need to have a Parse Tree for
that string. And, a derivation defines a
Parse Tree but it turns out that one Parse
Tree in general has many derivations and
in particular, we're interested in the
leftmost and rightmost derivations. These
are the two kinds of derivations that are
important in parser implementations.