[inaudible] Welcome back. At this video,
we're going to talk about how [inaudible]
expressions are used to construct a full
lexical specification on the programming
language. Before we get started, I want to
quickly summarize the notation for regular
expressions. One of the shorthand?s we
talked about last time is a+ which means a
sequence of at least 1a or the language
aa*. Sometimes you'll see a vertical bar
used instead of unions or a + b. Can also
be written a vertical bar b and optional a
is abbreviation for the regular expression
a + epsilon. And then we have character
ranges which allows us to do a big union,
a bunch of characters in order. And then
one more that's used, that's, that's
actually fairly important but we didn't
discussed last time is the compliment of
the character range. So this expression
here means any character except the
characters a through z. So the last
lecture, we talked about a specification
for the following predicate. Given a
string s, is it in the language as the
function l of a regular expression. As we,
we define the language of regular
expressions and talked about their
semantics in terms of sets of strings. And
so for any given regular expression, we
could reason out by hand whether a given
string was in that language or not, and
this turns out not to be enough for what
we wanted to do. So just to review, what
is it we wanted to do when we're given an
input, which is a bunch of characters, so
here's a string of characters And it can
be much longer than just setting
characters and. But we actually wanted to
do is to partition the string. We want to
drop lines in the strings, divide up into
the words of language. Now of course each
one of these words are to be The language
at some regular expression. But just
having a, a, a definition or a yes no
answers, not quite the same thing as
having a method for partitioning a string
into its constituting parts. And so we're
gonna have to adapt regular expressions,
to this problem and, and this requires
some small extensions and that's what this
video is all about. So let's talk about
how to do this. The first thing we're
going to do, when we want to design the
lexical specification of the language is
we have to write the regular expression,
for the lexing to be to the [inaudible]
classes and we, we talked about how to do
this last time. So, for the numbers we
might use digit plus desire as our regular
expression and we might have a category of
keywords which is just the list of all
the, keywords in the language. We would
have some category perhaps of identifiers.
There is the, definitely we talked about
it last time. Sequences of letters or
digits that begin with, with the letter
and then we're having a bunch of. Bunch of
punctuations, things like open parens,
close parens, etc. So we write down a
whole set of regular expressions. One for
each syntactic category in the language
and that's the starting point for our
lexical specification. The second step,
what we're going to do is we're going to
construct a gigantic regular expression
which just matches all the lexings for all
the tokens and this is just the union, of
all the regular expressions, that we wrote
out on the previous slides. So we'll just
take the union of all those regular
expressions and that forms, the lexical
specification of the language. And, we'll
just write this out, we don't really care
what these regular expressions are but
they're just some, set r1, r2 and so on
and the whole thing we're going to call r.
And now, here's the heart of how we
actually use this bicycle's specification
to perform lexical analysis. So, let's
consider an input. We input the string x1
up to xn. And now for every prefix of that
input, okay. We're going to check whether
it's in the language of the regular
expression. So we're gonna look at some
prefix trying with the first character and
we're gonna ask ourselves is it in the
language of that big regular expression.
And if it is, if it is in the language,
well then we know in particular that, that
prefix is in the language of one in the
constituen t regular expressions cuz
remember that r =. The sum of all the
different talking classes of our language,
okay. So we know that this prefix x1
through xi is in the language of sum rj.
Okay And so that we know that, that's a
word. In our language is one of. Is in one
of the talking classes that we're
interested in, And so what we do is we
simply delete that prefix from the input
and then we go back to three and we
repeat. And in this way we keep biting off
prefixes of the input and we'll do this
until the string is empty and then we have
[inaudible] analyzed the entire program.
Now this algorithm has a couple of
ambiguities or a couple of things that are
under specified and those are actually
interesting. So let's take a moment and
talk about those. The first question is
how much input is actually used? So, let's
consider the following situation. Let's
say that, we have, the x1 to xi, is in the
language of our lexical specification. And
let's say there's a different prefix,
that's also in the language of our lexical
specification and of course your I is, is
not equal to J. What does that look like?
Well, it would look like the following
kind of situation; we would have our input
string. And we have two different prefixes
of the input that are both valid talking
classes and the question is which one of
these do we want? And, you know just be
kind of [inaudible] here to have a
concrete example, let's consider. What
happens when a =,,,, = is at the, is at
the beginning of the input. After we
chopped off a bunch of other input and
perhaps we have this sub-string or this
prefix of the input that we're looking at
and the question is, you know should this
be regarded as a single = which would be
an assignment operator in most languages
or would it be regards to =,,,, = which in
some language is a comparison operator?
And, and this is an example we've looked
at before and discussed, and there's
actually a well defined answer to this
question. And, it is, that we should
always take the longer one and this has a
name that's c alled the maximal munch. So
the rule is that when faced with a choice
of two different prefixes of the input,
either which would be a valid token, we
should always choose the longer one. And,
the reason for this is that's just the way
humans themselves read things so when we
see =,,,, = we don't see two different
equal operators, we see =,,,, = and if I.
Look at, you know that the sentence that I
wrote up here, you know when we look at
HOW, we don't see three letters. We gather
that altogether in one long token. We go
as far as we can until we see a separator
and so because this is the way humans
work; we make the tools work the same way
and this normally or almost always does
the right thing. Second question is which
token should be used if more than one
token matches? So what do I mean by that?
Well, again we have our prefix of the
input and it's in the language of our
lexical specification and just remember
that the lexical specification itself
again is made up as the union, a bunch of
regular expressions for token classes.
Now, since that, since this prefix, is in
the language of the lexical, lexical
specification, that means that it again,
it must be in the language of some
particular token class, rj. But nothing
says that it isn't also in the language of
a completely different token class.
Meaning, at the same string could be
interpreted as a, as one of two different
tokens and the question is if this
happens, which one should we pick? So, for
example just to make this concrete, Recall
that we could have a lexical specification
for key words which would be things like
if and else, and so on, and also for
identifiers. And then the identifier was
the letter Followed by a letter or a
digit. Repeat it, okay. And if you look at
these two specifications, you'll see that
the string if, IF is both of them. So IF
is in the language of keywords, And it's
also in the language of the identifiers.
And so should we treat it as a keyword or
an identifier. Now the normal rule in most
languages is that if it's a keyword then i
t's always a keyword and you know the
identifier is actually don't include the
keywords. And but actually it's a real
pain to write out the identifiers in such
a way that you explicitly exclude the key
words. This is a much more natural
definition I've written here for the
identifiers. And so the way this gets
resolved is by a priority ordering and
typically the rule is to choose the one
Listed first. Okay. So when there is a
choice, when there is more than one token
class which the string might be long, the
one that is listed first is given higher
priority. So in our file defining our
lexical specification we would put the key
words before the identifiers just as we
have done here. The final question is what
to do if no rule matches. What if I have
the prefix of the input? That is not in
the language Of my lexical specification.
Now this can actually arise. Certainly
there are lots and lots of strings that
are not gonna be in the language of the
lexical specification of most languages.
And the question is how to handle that
situation? So it's very important for
compilers to do good error handling. They
can't simply crash. They need to be able
to give the user, the programmer a
feedback about where the error is and what
kind of error it is so we do need to
handle this gracefully. And the best
solution for lexical analysis is to not do
this so don't let this ever happen. And so
what we wanted to do instead is to write a
category of arrow strings, So, all of the
strings. Not in the lexical specification
of the language. So we write out a regular
expression. Again this is another regular
expression here. For all the possible
error strings, all the possible erroneous
strings that could occur as you know
invalid lexical input and then we put it
last. Put it last in priority. So that it
will match after everything else matches
and, and the reason for putting it last.
Is that, this actually allows us to be a
little bit sloppy in, in how we define the
error strings. It can actually overlap,
with earlier regular expressi ons. We can
include things in the error strings that
are in fact not errors. But, if we put it
last in priority, then it will only match
if no earlier regular expression match and
so in fact, they will only catch the error
strings. Then the action that we'll take
when we match the error string will be the
prints in the error message and give
device a feedback like where it is in the
file and such. To wrap up this video,
regular expressions are very nice and
concise notation for string patterns but
to use them in lexical analysis requires a
couple of small extensions. Some
particulars, a couple of ambiguities we
have to resolve, we want our matches to be
as long as possible. So we take. As much
input at a time as we can and we also want
to choose the highest Priority match. So,
the regular expressions are given a
priority. The different token classes have
priorities and, when there's tie, when the
same, prefix of the input could match more
than one, we pick the one that has the
highest priority. Typically this has done
just by listing them in order in a file
and the ones listed first have higher
priority over the ones listed later. I
just wanna warn you that when you go to
right lexical specifications, when you go
to actually implement, lexor for a
language, the interaction of these two
rules that we take longest possible
matches and we break ties and favor of the
highest priority rules. That this lead to
some tricky situations and it's not always
obvious that you're getting exactly what
you want, You have to think carefully
about the Ordering of the rules and it's
actually how you write the rules so that
you get the behavior that you desire. And
finally to handle errors, we typically
write out. Catch all regular expression
that soaks up all the possible erroneous
strings and give it the lowest priority so
that it only triggers if no valid token
class matches some piece of the input. If
I leave, we haven't discussed these yet
but they are very good algorithm to know
for implementing all of these and in fact
we'll be able to do it in only single pass
over the input and with very few
operations per character. Just a few, Just
a simple table look up and this would be
the subject of our future videos.